Wayne I. Pribble Papers
Wayne I. Pribble Papers
1946-1987
Pribble, Wayne I.
4.5 linear ft.
Collection includes the records of Wayne Pribble's companies, Barrier-Pribble and Pribble Plastics Products; mold drawings produced by Barrier-Pribble and Pribble Plastics Products; and drafts and papers related to Pribble and J. Harry DuBois' book, Plastics Mold Engineering.
2651147
Biographical History
Wayne I. Pribble was an American engineer, manufacturer, and author in the plastics field.
Pribble was a graduate of the General Electric Co. apprentice training program at Fort Wayne, Indiana. He was trained as a toolmaker but never practiced that profession and was instead employed as a mold designer by the Plastics Division of the General Electric Co. in Fort Wayne, 1937-1942. In 1942, he was promoted to product engineer and continued in that capacity until resigning in 1948 to form his own company.
Pribble formed Barrier-Pribble and Co., Inc. in 1948 with Alvis L. Barrier. In 1954, this company became Pribble Plastics Products, a custom mold maker specializing in thermosetting molding. Pribble Plastics Products closed in 1981 and was sold in 1983. Pribble went on to buy and sell hard-to-find used books and sell computer programs for Apple and IBM computers.
In collaboration with J. Harry DuBois, Pribble wrote the majority of the text for Plastics Mold Engineering, originally published by the American Technical Society of Chicago in 1946. The National Society of Plastics Engineers obtained publishing rights and issued a revised and enlarged text in 1965 as part of the Polymer Technology Series of SPE and published by Reinhold Publishing Company; a 3rd edition followed in 1978, and a 4th edition in 1987.
Pribble was a member of the Plastics Pioneers Association of the Society of the Plastics Industry, National Councilman for the Northern Indiana Section of the Society of Plastics Engineers, National Treasurer of the National Society of Plastics Engineers and recipient of the Society of Plastics Engineers Presidents Cup in 1948.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Wayne I. Pribble Papers includes the records of Wayne Pribble's companies, Barrier-Pribble and Pribble Plastics Products; mold drawings produced by Barrier-Pribble and Pribble Plastics Products; and drafts and papers related to Pribble and J. Harry DuBois' book, Plastics Mold Engineering.
Barrier-Pribble and Pribble Plastics Products contains company records, an annual appraisal, mold designs and records, a scrapbook, and related materials.
Drawings includes mold drawings for various plastic items and an index to the drawings.
Plastics Mold Engineering papers contains manuscripts, communications, research materials, purchasing orders and royalty receipts, galley proofs, reviewer comments and correspondences, and other materials related to the writing, editing, and publication of the book. The majority of materials are related to the 4th edition.
Arrangement of the Collection
Collection is arranged alphabetically by topic.
Related Material
has numerous holdings in the areas of plastics and industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing. In particular, see also the
J. Harry Dubois Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; Pribble, Wayne I.; DuBois, J. Harry (John Harry), 1903-; Barrier-Pribble (Firm); Van Nostrand Reinhold Company.; Pribble Plastics Products.; Plastics -- Molds.; Plastics industry and trade.; Thermosetting plastics.; Drawings (visual works); Drafts (documents); Business records.; Brochures.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Authors.; Engineers.; Manufacturers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from National Plastics Center and Museum, 11/06/2008. Originally, gift of Wayne Pribble, 1997.
Inventory
- Barrier-Pribble/Pribble Plastics Products
  - Appraisal report, 1973; Report of Pribble Plastics Products by Harding, Dahm & Company (Box 1)
  - Corporation record, 1948-1984; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - "Meet your staff", 1972; biographies of people involved in plastic injection molding die design (Box 1)
  - Mold designs, 1949; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Mold records: master sheets, 1956-1969 (Box 1)
  - Operating instructions and press equipment, 1956-1963 (Box 1)
  - PPP scrapbook, 1959-1979 (Oversize 1)
- Drawings
  Large schematic drawings of molds for a wide range of plastic items. Originally donated in a five-shelf flat file, the original shelving order and groupings have been retained. Although the larger drawings are numbered, some drawers contained smaller unnumbered drawings; these have been kept with the numbered drawings from that drawer on the presumption that they relate somehow to the numbered drawings.
  - Index to mold drawings, 3 boxes (Oversize 1)
  - Mold drawings, #1100-1221, 1950-1981; includes 1 roll of unnumbered drawings (Map-case 93)
  - Mold drawings, #1505-1602, 1700-1761, 1950-1981; includes 1 folder of unnumbered drawings (Map-case 94)
  - Mold drawings, #1762-1799, 8000-8069, 1950-1981; includes 1 folder of unnumbered drawings (Map-case 95)
  - Mold drawings, #8070-8161, 1950-1981; includes 1 roll of unnumbered drawings (Map-case 96)
  - Mold drawings, #8162-8342, 1950-1981; includes 1 roll of unnumbered drawings (Map-case 109)
- Plastics Mold Engineering papers
  - 3rd edition: education, 1983; information about the book's use in a plastics mold design and theory course (Box 1)
  - 3rd edition: figures, 1973; 1975,; undated (Box 1)
  - 3rd edition: royalties, 1975-1982; 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - 3rd edition: miscellaneous, 1971-1983; 2 folders; communications, purchase orders, article clippings, and manuscript reviews with responses (Box 1)
  - 4th edition: appendix, 1986 (Box 2)
  - 4th edition: caption and figure list, 1986 (Box 2)
  - 4th edition: chapter 1, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - 4th edition: chapter 2, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - 4th edition: chapter 3, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - 4th edition: chapter 4, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - 4th edition: chapter 5, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - 4th edition: chapter 6, 1986-1987; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 4th edition: chapter 7, 1986-1987; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 4th edition: chapter 8, 1985-1987; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 4th edition: chapter 9, 1986 (Box 3)
  - 4th edition: chapter 10, 1984; 1987 (Box 3)
  - 4th edition: chapter 10, 1980; 1983-1984,; 1986-1987; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - 4th edition: chapter 11, 1985-1987; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 4th edition: chapter 12, 1976; 1982,; 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - 4th edition: chapter 12, 1986-1987 (Box 5)
  - 4th edition: chapter 13, 1984; 1987 (Box 5)
  - 4th edition: chapter 14, 1981; 1984,; 1987 (Box 5)
  - 4th edition: glossary, 1980 (Box 5)
  - 4th edition: index, 1984; 1987 (Box 5)
  - 4th edition: preface, 1987 (Box 5)
  - 4th edition: proofs and editing, 1985; 1987; editing key, galley proofs, and notes (Box 5)
  - 4th edition: reviews, 1984; 1986; manuscript reviewer comments and Pribble's response (Box 5)
  - 4th edition: table of contents, 1987 (Box 5)
  - 4th edition: research files: CAD/CAM, 1979-1984; 2 folders; conference papers, advertisements, correspondence, and magazine clippings related to computer-aided design/manufacture (Box 5)
  - 4th edition: research files: CAD/CAM, 1982; 1984; conference papers, advertisements, correspondence, and magazine clippings related to computer-aided design/drafting/manufacture/engineering (Box 6)
  - 4th edition: research files: miscellaneous, 1974; 1978,; 1983,; 1985-1987; 2 folders; magazine and journal clippings, brochures, and information packets (Box 6)
  - 5th edition material, 1983; 1986-1987; research materials and communications relating to finding an editor for the 5th edition (Box 6)
  - Communications: J. Harry Dubois, 1963-1965; 1976-1980,; 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - Communications: miscellaneous, 1946-1974 (Box 6)
  - Photographs, 1946; 1964,; undated (Box 6)